NARRATOR: Previously on Gotham:
FAIRCHILD: Unh. BULLOCK:
The guys call him The Ogre.
He's a serial killer.
Whoever did this,
he's a monster.
The blood of his next
victim is on my hands.
If you don't drop it, that
blood could be Lee's.
The Ogre retaliates against
any cop who investigates him...
kills the people they love.
The man who stabbed
Alfred, he's in Gotham.
And you need my
help to find him.
Who sent you?
You want me to tell
Bunderslaw you're onto him?
[REGGIE SCREAMS]
MAN: Hey.
You look far from home.
Get away from him.
Or what?
[SCOFFS]
Whatever.
SELINA: Come on.
- Did you go back?
- Yeah. The cops are there.
And?
And? What do you think?
He fell out of a five-story
window. He's dead.
Why did you do it?
He told us what we wanted, about
Bunderslaw. You didn't have to...
I did. The moment we left,
he was gonna tell his boss!
Who works for you, by the way.
He's the one who tried to kill
me, who tried to kill your butler...
who probably
killed your parents.
I saved your life.
Besides, you wanted to do it
too, you just didn't have the guts.
- Wait...
- Just go home.
We still have to find out who
Bunderslaw is and what we wants.
You mean, you do.
You really think this is over?
He's gonna come after us.
So, what's next? Hm?
- His safe.
- What?
Every senior executive at
Wayne Enterprises has a safe.
Any secrets Bunderslaw
has, that's where they'll be.
- Key or combination?
- Key.
My dad had one.
He'll probably
keep it on him, then.
Figure out a way to get
me close, and I'll steal it.
- Can you do that?
- I think so.
And what happened tonight...
you tell no one.
Not your buddy,
Detective Gordon.
Not your butler.
No one.
Punctures on test subject are
consistent with those on the victim...
indicating the killer
was right-handed.
Yum.
Where's Thompkins?
Detective Gordon, Dr. Thompkins
said I was free to use this room.
She's nice, not like the
old medical examiner...
Ed, just tell me where she is.
No riddles.
Home. She went home.
Hope you find her.
[BUZZING]
[GLASS SHATTERS
THEN LESLIE GASPS]
Jim?
Jim, is that you?
[CAT MEOWS THEN LESLIE GASPS]
You're lucky I don't skin you.
Go on.
[DIALING]
[CELL PHONE RINGS]
[LESLIE GASPS THEN
GORDON GRUNTS]
- All right, slow down.
- Lee, please.
Start over.
This case you caught, the dead woman,
she was murdered by a serial killer?
Yes. He's killed a dozen
women, maybe more.
- And Loeb gave you this on purpose?
- He wants to hurt me.
And how am I in danger?
He murders the loved ones of
any cop who investigates him.
That's how he's been able
to get away with it so far.
Anyone who comes after him...
he's killed someone they love,
and the investigation's been buried.
Bullock knows a cop who
came home and found his wife.
Her throat had been cut.
Oh.
That's why Loeb
gave me the case.
Either I give up
like everyone else...
and live knowing I
let a killer go free...
or I keep going...
and someone I love is killed.
- You're not giving up, are you?
- I can't.
That's why I need you to
get out of Gotham right now.
Tonight.
No.
You wanna protect me? Find him.
I'm gonna stay
here and do my job.
But I do like that you
think of me as a loved one.
I do.
Love you.
It only took a serial killer
to get you to say that.
[PEOPLE CHATTERING]
LENNON: Thanks.
- No problem.
[DANCE MUSIC PLAYS
OVER SPEAKERS]
Hi.
[DOOR OPENS THEN CLOSES]
BARBARA: This is it.
Home sweet, you know?
This is a great space.
Selina.
- Hm. Sort of a roommate.
- Hm.
She comes and goes.
- Wayne Enterprises Charity Ball.
- Hm.
Didn't you know I'm
a member of society?
I go every year, get my
picture taken in a pretty dress.
Smile.
Aren't you scared
of my being here?
Should I be?
Are you dangerous?
I don't know. Is your
boyfriend gonna come home?
I never said I had a boyfriend.
I assumed a woman
as beautiful as you...
You assumed I had a boyfriend...
and you assumed I would be the
kind of woman who would cheat on him.
Well, I'm not.
And I don't have a boyfriend.
And if a bus hit me tomorrow...
no one would care.
- That change things?
- Yes, actually, it does.
Make it more illicit?
Or would there be less chance of us
getting attached one night and done?
Only that would happen anyway,
because once you saw the real me...
you would run screaming,
like everyone else.
I have to say, you're not
who I imagined you would be.
Surprise.
You can let yourself out.
[SINGING] Love, love
Love
But you promised
to dance with me.
And I will. But first, I have
to finish with that gentleman.
Who knew running a
nightclub was so much work?
My poor darling.
But the soul is not deceived
In this world...
As I was saying...
you and your crew are the
best gun and knifemen in the city.
Your hit on Councilman Klein...
a thing of beauty.
- I'm a fan.
- Cheers.
What do you want?
For you to help me kill Don
Maroni and all of his lieutenants.
You're having a laugh.
I'm fairly certain I'm not.
And Falcone's good with this?
He will be when it's done.
Thank you. No thank you.
So you like being number two.
Falcone gives Victor Zsasz
first dibs on every new contract.
You bring him the bullet-riddled corpse
of his enemy and all of that will change.
This is your chance to move up.
[CHUCKLING]
You're a mad fellow, aren't you?
Fair enough.
Come by the bar tomorrow...
we'll talk details.
- What's this about, Harvey?
BULLOCK: Have a seat.
This is my partner, Jim Gordon.
Detective, eight years ago...
you investigated the murder of
a woman named Julie Kemble.
- Yeah, that was a long time
ago. GORDON: It was The Ogre.
Julie Kemble
was his first victim.
But you dropped
the investigation...
and because of that, 11 more
women have been murdered.
- Seriously, guys, you know...
- Stop.
We also know The Ogre kills the loved
ones of the cops that hunt him down.
That pattern started with you.
We think you found
something that spooked him.
Your notes from
the investigation.
The last page, something's
been scratched out.
I wanna know what.
He killed my wife.
I still got a daughter, Harvey.
Beth Tudor.
Katherine Wood.
Jessica Parker.
Eleven women.
Each one was someone's daughter.
It has to stop.
Yeah. I was doing
background on the dead girl.
Someone told me she was a nurse
for a private medical clinic uptown.
It's on Grant and 80th,
some cosmetic place.
We'll put cops on your
daughter until this is done.
[CAMERA SHUTTER CLICKS]
- So you forgive
me? KRINGLE: Mm.
- I'll see you tonight.
KRINGLE: Mm-hm.
- How's it hanging, Riddle Man?
- Uh, it's hanging...
fine.
Mr. Nygma, did you
need something?
Oh, yes. Uh...
Detective Gordon wanted me to go through
the forensic evidence of these old murders.
Are those bruises?
Uh...
Did Officer Dougherty do that?
Um, he was upset, and he didn't mean
to. I said some things I shouldn't have.
Miss Kringle, this is
not right. He can't just...
Mr. Nygma.
It is none of your concern.
Now, I need to get
started on these files, so...
Alfred. Should you be up?
Thank you, Master Bruce.
I feel... I feel much better.
Can I get you anything?
Yes, actually. I've decided to attend the
Wayne Enterprises Charity Ball tonight.
All the senior
management will be there.
People should see that a Wayne
is still the head of the company.
I shall set your
tux out for you.
- Alfred.
- Yes, Master Bruce?
When you were in the army...
you had to kill people, right?
Yes. Yes, I did.
And it was necessary?
I see. So you overheard
the conversation that
Reggie and I had that
was best left unsaid.
But in answer to
your question, yes.
Yes, it was necessary.
Now, if you'll excuse me, I better find
my good cuff links if we're stepping out.
No, but you're still recovering.
What, I'm supposed to let you
walk into that nest of vipers?
There'll be hundreds of people
there, Alfred. I won't be in any danger.
So you say, but you're
not gonna go alone.
I won't be alone.
I've invited Selina Kyle.
Selina Kyle?
To the Wayne Enterprises Ball?
I see.
What do you see?
Nothing. I mean, you know,
you're a healthy young lad...
and she's a pretty girl with a
penchant of wearing too much leather...
- Alfred, it's not like that.
- Then what's it like?
Well, what if it is, huh?
What's wrong with that?
Absolutely nothing.
So I will wait in the car outside
so you don't feel my watchful eye.
But I will be close
by if the need's be.
That is the deal.
Fine.
Could you call around and send some
dresses and shoes to where she's staying?
This is the address.
It's a charity ball, Alfred.
I'll be fine.
BULLOCK: Freaky, huh?
I wonder how they
recognize themselves after.
Doc Thompkins is fine.
No one's gonna touch
her at the precinct. Relax.
You do understand it's because
of me that she's in danger?
Anything that
happens is my fault.
You can't hold yourself responsible
for the actions of a psychopath.
Sure I can.
Detectives. I'm Dr. Cushman.
How can I help you?
We're looking into the murder
of a woman named Julie Kemble.
- She worked here about eight years
ago. CUSHMAN: Of course. Terrible thing.
Julie was a talented nurse.
But she'd only just started
here when it happened.
She'd been recommended
by one of our patients.
- Patient's name?
- I'm afraid I can't give you that.
Confidentiality.
BULLOCK: Really?
You're gonna make
us get a warrant?
Yes.
"I specialize in fake boobs, but
I got ethics, I need a warrant."
We'll talk to Judge
Harkness. I'm sure...
That car was in
front of the precinct.
BULLOCK: Jim, wait up.
[ENGINE STARTS]
[TIRES SCREECHING]
- You sure about this?
- It was him.
- You saw his face?
- No.
I should've been looking for a tail.
It's obvious he tracks our investigations.
Called in a description of
the car and a partial plate.
So, what's the next move?
Gordon. You got a
call, says it's urgent.
GORDON: Gordon. LENNON
[OVER PHONE]: Detective.
I didn't get to say hello
properly in the alley.
- Listen to me.
- Don't bother tracing this.
I'm giving you one
chance to turn yourself in.
You make me come after
you and I will put you down.
Something tells me you've
begun to buy your own press.
The hero cop who's gonna clean up
Gotham. The rising star of the G.C.P.D.
- I'll stop you, that's for damn sure.
- No, detective, you won't.
Keep on, and I will
kill someone you love.
This is your only warning.
[LINE CLICKS THEN DIAL TONE]
Oh, no. Tell me that wasn't him.
He's used to intimidating cops. We
have to show him we're not afraid.
And how do we do that?
- You're okay with this, you're sure?
- Yes.
It's the right thing to do.
[CAMERA SHUTTERS CLICKING]
I called you here today...
because the people of
Gotham deserve to know
that there's a serial
killer in their midst.
For years, he's
killed with impunity...
aided by a culture of silence
and fear among the police.
That ends now.
We'll be providing the names
and photos of all of the victims.
Please call with
any information.
And to the man who
committed these horrific crimes...
your days of hiding are over.
I'm coming after you...
and I'm not gonna stop.
What are those for?
The Wayne Charity Ball.
It's boring but good for
the gallery's business.
Well, I'll probably
see you there.
[KNOCK ON DOOR]
What?
I'm going with Bruce Wayne.
Wait, what?
MAN 1: Delivery for
Selina Kyle. SELINA: Oh.
Uh, over there.
MAN 2: Thank you. Enjoy.
Am I really supposed
to wear these?
Okay. We have
a lot of work to do.
Got it. That was the doctor.
Harkness sent over the warrant.
The dead girl came to the clinic by
way of a Miss Constance Van Groot.
Van Groot? That's one of
Gotham's oldest families. Shipping.
We thought The Ogre might be
rich. Could be the old lady had a son.
GORDON: You got an address?
- Right here.
WOMAN [SINGING]:
You're the cream in my coffee
Well, Butch, Connor
and his crew are onboard.
- They hate Maroni even more than I...
- Shut up.
Maroni and his crew are here.
- I couldn't turn them away.
- Of course. No matter...
No. She was already here.
MARONI: Is that my buddy Oswald?
- Come here.
- Oh, Oswald.
WOMAN [SINGING]: You
will always be my necessity
I'd be lost without you
[MARONI CHUCKLES]
There he is.
Mother, what are you doing?
- I am having a drink with Mister...
- Ah, ah, ah.
I told you. Sal.
With Sal.
- But we shouldn't impose any longer...
- Ah, ah, ah.
- You're not taking my Gertrud.
- Oh, his Gertrud. Heh-heh-heh.
Sit. Join us.
GERTRUD: Oswald, sit.
Sit, Oswald.
[KNOCK ON DOOR]
Hello.
I'm Bruce Wayne.
- Barbara Kean. BRUCE: Oh.
Selina never said you're
who she's staying with.
Detective Gordon spoke of you.
Well, Selina can
be a little guarded.
- Yes, I know. SELINA:
Stop talking about me.
Selina...
You look very nice.
The shoes hurt.
Have fun. Look
for me at the ball.
It was nice meeting you.
Think she's here?
Miss Van Groot?
G.C.P.D.
I need to say this
is not exactly legal.
We're running out of time.
[CLATTERING]
[GASPING]
Over here.
He's good.
Call it in. I'm gonna go
check the rest of the house.
He told me...
but I was too slow.
Hello?
Miss Van Groot?
I'm a police officer.
Oh.
Gordon!
Jim!
Jim Gordon...
Constance Van Groot.
[CLASSICAL MUSIC
PLAYS OVER SPEAKERS]
[PEOPLE CHATTERING]
Everyone's staring at us.
Well, I am Bruce Wayne.
Well, I am.
I don't see Bunderslaw anywhere.
He's probably not coming.
But he's on the guest list.
Just keep dancing.
And smile, maybe.
Name's Jacob Skolimski.
He's not talking, but near as we
can tell he was the old lady's butler.
You think The Ogre's this
guy's son, not the dead woman's?
Yeah. Coroner said the old
bird's been dead for years.
My guess, Ogre killed her,
daddy pretends she's alive...
so his crazy serial killer son
can keep living off her money.
He tried to kill himself.
He knew you were closing in. He
has to be in contact with his son.
Yeah. Listen, Gordon's running
pretty hot on this one, cap.
Can you blame him? Thinks
Thompkins is the next victim.
Still, watch him.
Alvarez called.
Nothing on the
son in the system.
We have to make him talk.
GORDON: Make this simple. Give
us your son's name and address.
JACOB: Or what?
I'm not afraid of you.
Only because you don't know me.
Listen, I get wanting
to protect your son.
But how many more
women will he have to kill
before you realize he
needs to be locked up?
What are you talking about?
Don't play dumb with me. You were hiding
a rotting corpse upstairs for years...
but no, no, my son's an angel.
He didn't murder close to a
dozen women that we know of.
My son, he made
one mistake. One.
Anything else is lies.
So tell us the truth.
[PEOPLE CHATTERING]
Selina, what
happened last night...
- can't happen again.
- I didn't have a choice.
I don't accept that.
[SELINA SCOFFS]
I knew you wouldn't
be able to handle it.
You're right.
- I did wanna kill him.
- Keep your voice down.
But there's a line, Selina.
You can say I don't have guts...
but the fact is I
will never cross it.
I guess that's where
we're different, then.
Because if I had to
do it again, I would.
And it wouldn't
bother me one bit.
[INAUDIBLE DIALOGUE]
That's Bunderslaw.
[CHATTERING]
[CLEARS THROAT]
- Riddle Man.
- Officer Dougherty, a word.
I can start a war or end one.
I can give you the strength of
heroes or leave you powerless.
I might be snared with a glance,
but no force can compel me to stay.
What am I?
- You got me.
- Love.
Miss Kringle has given hers to
you, and in return you hurt her.
- I saw the bruises.
- And?
And you cannot do that.
- The next time you do that, I'll...
DOUGHERTY: Whoa, whoa, whoa.
Calm down. You'll
give yourself a girly fit.
Have you ever been with a woman?
Didn't think so.
They need a firm hand.
That goes double for
Kringle. The girl's got a tongue.
I won't let you hurt her.
[LAUGHS]
Oh, yeah?
What are you gonna do?
[CLICKS TONGUE]
That's what I thought.
Later, Riddle Man.
[CLASSICAL MUSIC
PLAYS OVER SPEAKERS]
Care to dance?
- You.
- Me.
JACOB: It was not a
place for a boy to grow up.
Miss Van Groot kept herself
sealed off from the world...
but she doted on my son.
Treated him as her own.
Still, I... I didn't realize
how deep it went.
This kid's mom was out of the
picture, so he started thinking...
he was this Van Groot
woman's secret son.
I tried to tell him it wasn't true,
but he had built this fantasy...
and Miss Van Groot led him on.
She was deranged. Cruel, even.
So about 10 years
ago, he confronts her.
He demands that she acknowledge him, give
him her last name, put him in the will.
She laughs at him.
Said it was all just a
big joke. So he kills her.
His dad feels guilty,
helps him cover it up.
So the old woman rejects
him, he kills her, bang.
You got a serial killer with a
mommy-didn't-love-me complex.
But there's a wrinkle.
I don't know where my son is.
He called today, told me
the police would be coming.
But I haven't seen him since
the day he killed Miss Van Groot.
My son is not a bad man.
Your son has been seducing and
killing women for almost a decade.
[LAUGHING]
Why is he laughing?
My son? Seducing women?
Let me show you my son. Two
pictures. That's all I managed to save.
You've heard "a face
only a mother could love"?
Well, his mother couldn't.
She left us after he was born.
Oh, yes. My son...
the seducer.
It makes sense he scratched
his face out of those pictures.
But that means this
can't be The Ogre.
We're chasing the wrong guy.
Jim had an idea.
Judge Harkness'
warrant was very specific.
- I don't have to say anything.
- Then nod.
Did you operate on this man?
I need to know what he looks like now,
or the next woman he kills will be on you.
[CLASSICAL MUSIC
PLAYS OVER SPEAKERS]
Never, never would he
play with other children.
He knew even then he
was too good for them.
And now he is a
respectable man of business...
my Oswald.
Well, this has been a delight.
But it's late.
One thing...
Gertrud, my love.
- Oh.
- A question that's been bothering me.
Oh, no. Oh, no.
Is this an act?
[GERTRUD AND MARONI CHUCKLE]
Are you pretending that
he's just a nightclub owner?
- Or are you really that stupid?
- Stop!
I don't understand. I...
- Your son...
- Don Maroni, I am warning you!
- Is a coldblooded psychopath.
- No, no, no.
I can't count how
many men he's killed.
My own friend, Frankie Carbone,
he stabbed him a dozen times.
What kind of person plunges a
knife into someone over and over?
He's a filthy liar, Mother!
He's just angry because
I played him for a fool.
[GERTRUD GASPS]
You know, don't you?
- I can see it.
- Let go of her!
Did you catch him one night
washing blood from his hands?
When did you realize that you
had given birth to a monster?
GERTRUD: Aah! Aah!
You're going to pay for this.
Maybe.
Or maybe this ends with me
dumping your lifeless body into the river.
Either way, you and Mama
Gertrud can stop pretending.
The place is looking good.
Shh, shh, shh.
The other night, when
you saw my invitation,
why didn't you tell
me you were coming?
I wasn't. I didn't get invited.
Oh, so you're crashing.
Oh, no, I'm on the list.
It's amazing what a
$10,000 donation will do.
You donated
$10,000 to this? Why?
I was hoping that
would be apparent.
And what if I
decided not to come?
Well, then, I'd have been making
a generous donation to charity...
and I would have
been very disappointed.
[DOOR OPENS THEN CLOSES]
The way things ended
last night, it was my fault.
But I felt something.
I couldn't let it slip away.
Well, that's very sweet, but...
You said that when people see
the real you, they run screaming.
Someone said the same thing to me
once, that no one would ever love me.
- Who?
- The woman I thought was my mother.
Barbara, I know
what it's like...
to be one person on the inside
and have the world see another.
I lived like that...
and it almost destroyed me.
I can see it destroying you.
I don't wanna dance anymore.
The person that I am now...
I created.
I brought him into being.
I can do the same for you.
Aren't you tired
of playing games?
Of hiding?
Yes.
MAN 1: Goodbye.
MAN 2: See you soon.
- Hello. I'm Bruce Wayne.
- Sid Bunderslaw.
BRUCE: I'm going around trying to get to
know everybody who works for the company.
- You work for Wayne Enterprises,
don't you? BUNDERSLAW: I do.
I'm the Director of
Physical Operations...
which I'm afraid is a bit dull.
There are many much
more interesting people here.
Well, I'm sure I'll get to
meet everyone eventually.
Forgive me, Bruce, I have
an early flight tomorrow.
It's been a pleasure.
It was, um...
It was nice meeting you.
SELINA: Sorry.
[BRUCE SIGHS]
See? Nothing to it.
What is it?
Nothing.
Stop right there, buster.
Riddle Man? What the hell are
you doing creeping around here?
- You need to leave Miss Kringle alone.
- What?
I'm not gonna let you
hurt her, ever again.
I think you need to
leave Gotham tonight.
[LAUGHING]
I get it now.
You got a thing for my girl.
That's too funny.
Don't take this personal.
[NYGMA GRUNTS THEN COUGHS]
Aw.
[DOUGHERTY LAUGHS]
You want some more?
Upsy-daisy! Unh!
Oh, dear.
[GRUNTING]
Riddle Man...
Oh, dear.
Oh, no.
[LAUGHS]
Oh, dear.
[LAUGHING]
- Oswald.
- Feeling better?
I made tea.
I'm afraid you had, well,
heh, a little too much to drink.
Mr. Maroni, he... He has
a strange sense of humor...
Oswald.
I am not some bumpkin from
the country with hay in my brains.
- No.
- I am your mother...
and I will love you
no matter what.
But lie to me now...
and you will break my heart.
Oswald...
have you done things...
you should not?
Mother...
I'm a nightclub owner. Hm?
That's all.
I'm tired now.
I am tired.
[SOBBING]
[KNOCKING ON DOOR]
Yeah, I got a delivery
for Gertrud from Sal.
Tip's not included.
You tell Sal it's over.
The guns are bought.
The killing room is waiting.
He doesn't know it,
but he's a dead man.
On second thought,
I'll tell him myself.
[GRUNTING]
GERTRUD: Oswald?
Who was that?
It's Mr. Yatsko from next door.
He needs help
taking out some trash.
GERTRUD: You... You...
Please, you help him, then.
Jason Van Groot?
His real name is Jason Skolimski. He
used the old woman's name at the clinic.
But there's no Jason Van Groot or
Skolimski in Gotham. The guy's a ghost.
So the old woman rejects
him, he goes to the doctor...
gets himself a pretty new face.
That's where he
runs into the nurse.
And we're off to the races.
- I don't suppose you got a picture?
- Missing from the file. No surprise there.
But the good doctor was
kind enough to do a sketch.
It's been 10 years since he
last saw him, but it's a start.
So we have his real name,
but not what alias he's using...
or what he looks like
beyond a decade-old sketch.
Did he say anything
else on the phone today?
- Anything we might have missed?
GORDON: No, just wanted me to back off.
Told me not to believe my own
press as the rising star of the G.C.P.D.
What is it?
The paper that said that...
they ran an old photo
of me from a charity gala.
I wasn't alone.
[KNOCKING ON DOOR]
GORDON: Barbara?
Is Barbara here?
- No. Why?
- Where is she?
When's the last
time you saw her?
At the Wayne Ball.
She left with some guy.
- Was this the guy?
- That's kind of a crappy drawing.
Was this the guy?
Yeah, I think so.
Why? Who is he?
What's through there?
See for yourself.
[English - US -SDH]